so this is the shorter note on the Bona
the opinion has been expressed in ETS
dictionary that Nibbana is not
transcendental if by transcendental is
meant mystical either in the sender
going to do with his divine ground
personally be in the nature of a mystery
and Nirvana or extinction is not
transcendental indeed is anti
transcendental for mystification so we
talk about this often like mystical
kinds of thinking now that's not correct
to do what exactly is it you clarified
what makes thought review mystical non
mr.koravit rational means means what we spoke
rational means means what we spoke
before means assuming it outside of your
experience which in itself something you
can't even conceive even as a theory
which is why it's a contradiction in
terms so mysticism will be the counterpart or
so mysticism will be the counterpart or
the equally external view of scientific
projection of the public world well you
can either take it in that direction
direction of matter when you say it's
all just electrons and atoms and
chemistry and what not
oh you can take any the automatic but
from the same point of view of that
external external to the experience is
about you assume there is something
Atari you assume that you can assume the
external and hence it's mystical
and there usually is pretty much
relative to common thread in in any
mystical religious no matter how
different it might be on the particular
manifestation saw it as a threat of
review underneath it's that it's that
very thing assuming the external
external entity external realms external
and that's when they say transcendental
that's usually what's meant when a fire
becomes extinguished because there is
there's that prominent wrong view of
people assuming once the flame
extinguishes it kind of goes further but
see any notion of further means you
assuming the possibility of a realm
outside of this the five aggregates the
experience as a whole
yet that assumption is within the five
aggravating experience as a whole as the
Buddha said you cannot step outside of
it but far near up or down big or small
the five aggregates are there and if you
remember the eons of previous lives you
remember within these five aggregates of
one among them so the notion of external
to it it's already something that we
perceived as such it's already something
that's thoroughly
within the five aggregates it's one of
them so instead of assuming the
extinction of the flame assuming the the
sort of the projection into some another
realm of invisible no matter how
ambiguous you still perceive it as such
which means it's it's a gratuitous
assumption that you cannot actually
experience so instead of that it's just
the simile of the Nibbana being the
extinguishing the flame is exactly that
extinguishing of the flame absence of
fire absence of greed aversion delusion
absence of burning burning flames that's
it there is no more now where their
absence gone or something
later on in the note he mentions how it
can be thought of as transient
transcendental in the sense of being
outside the realm of rational
investigation are you transcend greed
aversion delusion you transcend
ignorance yeah so in that sense it's
transcendental within the family but you
cannot transcend the five aggregates and
why would you why would you quit because
as the Buddha said up or down is not the
five aggregates so they are not a
problem these are elasti nearly 3500 glades the
these are elasti nearly 3500 glades the
operon is there so you transcending the
five aggregates and finding some hidden
realm well you'll be carrying your Rupa
runner with you you're trying to get rid
of
that which is not a problem
by mistaking it to be a problem
he goes on to make some points about the
word Luther itself the first one
mentioning how there's you know there's
no figure the reason why I am why I
exist hence one can rationally reason
out and escape from it more interested
in the second part of which reads I can
assert my existence or I can deny it but
in order to do either I must be pissed
or did I myself who assert for denying
and he attempted me to abolish man has
been tacitly confirmed it party that's
what the extension philosophers meant
when they said the existence precedes
the essence any essence you might have
it's given on the basis of existence so
you cannot rationalize outside of your
existence because that's in itself the
active rationalization is something
within the existing experience as a
whole
this is from
footnote see these basic talked about
the idea of that people try and find
some positive hope in navona somehow
even if they even person to say
otherwise he says the suitors are less
he says the suitors are less
accommodating see ahjumma ahjumma nicaya
for an account of the eternalists unruly
banks face a subjective non-being upon
hearing the Buddha's teachings
extinction the apprehends annihilation
despairs it follows beating his breast
period but not so the audience alphabet
so I was gonna go happy that this person
who kisses is clinging to views and at
the same time understood that but is
teaching to the extent forgiven because
because it's within the five elements as
a whole because within the experience
it's not it's not the hidden realm
that's been obscured by some veil of
ignorance so it is within this
experience so a person can and there are
the suitors well you could have said the
person thinks oh I'm attending the Barna
Disney Banias mine as in with the wrong
view with the wrong attitude with
appropriation he's actually having the
experience of non-green on a version on
delusion and he recognizes it as the
experience and on grade on aversion and
delusion but he doesn't enter it as a
Buddha would say because what he's on
free from greed will delusion but that
experience the experience of absence of
greed aversion delusion
he's a real phenomenon negative
phenomena by the real as such so those
people would get the hint of that but
they would be terrified because they
would see it through the assumption of a
degree of being the degree of positivity
that is necessary for their existence
anything less than positivity that they
have assumed which is pooper than
departure borrow basically any anything
less than that is going to be terrifying
is going to be bringing anxiety it's
going to bring in fear and and that's
what I mean by by by discerning negative
appearing as negative not trying to make
it positive not trying to overtly assume
it into positive you are actually
undoing your dependence upon a certain
degree over of a positivity of a
phenomenon so in that sense if there is
fear at face in the face of Nibbana it's
because your assumption of being is
being contradicted now because you
recognize that there are other things
lower than the threshold or what you
deem to be existence that is it and
their way out of your control way out of
your comfort zone way out of anything
that you've been concealing so far way
out of my sense of mine
and that's why I just results in an
instant dread so Nibbana really it's
it's work its what death is for Apple to
Gina if Apatow Gina that's what that's
why they would jump into a coma that
will kill us they will destroy us
because for Petrosian our death is that
direction of not mine
annihilation out of my control that's
going to affect this life within these
five aggregates so really that's why
money a mindfulness of death is one of
the quickest ways of becoming in other
hands but obviously can be a bit risky
as well
or they were not that non born become
non made undetermined escape here from
the bore and become me determined would
not be manifest and also could be a sin
to death and destruction monks lost this
is called an undetermined
and it see it seemed that whenever we
talk about navona it's always kind of
even in these negative terms like an
abscess an on something
so is is there some positive thing we
can think of as an opponent or is it
well that absence is positive positive
in its absence absence it's a it's a
it's a manifested phenomenon and as such
from that point of view it is a positive
thing another positive thing in a sense
of becoming an object of your senses for
example which is usually where people
regard as a positive thing that's why
that's what I mean
you need to learn how to allow tense
thoughts feelings perceptions to endure
not just fall into kind of explaining
them and or trying to get rid of them or
sort of rationalize them by allowing
things to do you see them with the exist
on their own accord they persist on
their own accord and by being able to do
that you will see that absences persist
on their own accord negative presence
possess on its own accord and as such
it's something the negative aspect is is
basically a counter definition of
consciousness with the ultimate negative
so that's why the negative in its most
general whether it's a negative
particular thing or more general thing
the negative is there which means the
aggregate of consciousness is there so
that's why the Barna would would equate
to the extinguishing of that indications
caused by consciousness the non
indicative consciousness as the
innovator translated it so in that sense
negative exists as negative but people
usually associate for complaint
existence with a positive or with the
degrees of positive which is the degrees
of bhava basically so I'm doing the
bhava makes you clarifies the
the correct way of appearing negative
the positive aspects of negativity so
that's when a banner is dama
but it's the asana the Dhamma is the
Dhamma that you experience through
extinguishing determinations
determinations of greed aversion
delusion so the absence of that which
used to be a burning fire is a real
experience
but if in our stewing minds we still
can't help feeling that navona really
often somehow be some eternity of
positive enjoyment for at least of
experience when we ponder these two
suited vestiges first one says there are
a month at least three feelings stated
by me
wasn't feeling unpleasant feeling
neither unpleasant or Pleasant feeling
these three feelings have been stated by
me but this month has been stated by me
whatever is phelps counts is
unpleasurable suffered that cowbird was
sent by me concerning the impermanence
of determinations and then the venerable
sariputta said this is extinction
friends that equivalent this extinction
friend that is better and this was said
the ener-blue died incentive to the
venerable sorry quick death but what
here in a pleasant and sorry but since
here and there is nothing felt just this
is lemon trend adhere in there is
nothing felt so
so
these two suitors seem to be trying to
point that the idea when the bonnet is
in reference to feelings well one the
first bit talks about from the point of
view of you to Gina the other one talks
from the point of view of another hat so
from a point of view to Gina who has she
still has craving you got a pleasure
craving you got the world in pain that
in order to overcome that he needs to
regard any arising of feeling as
affected by craving any arising of
feeling as a problem any arising of
feeling as arising of suffering there is
a problem there is suffering so that's
why whatever it's felt counts as as
pleasurable because with that kind of
attitude he will then be draw from we
draw the notion of ownership of his own
feelings and the notion of ownership of
control that's why the impermanence of
of the determinations the determination
for craving is the feeling so seeing
that these feelings part anita they
cannot be on
will then result in in fading away of
Kramer from the point of view of other
hand the fact that he not none of the
none of the feelings can affect him and
he is fully understood that and fully
experienced it and fully verified it
that in itself is very pleasant the fact
that he doesn't feel anything it is very
good